Malcolm S. Knowles Papers
Malcolm S. Knowles Papers
1930-1985,
1951-1985
Knowles, Malcolm S. (Malcolm Shepherd), 1913-1997.
33 linear ft.
Contains Knowles's personal and professional papers: biographical data, correspondence, photographs, printed and published material, scrapbooks, speeches, meeting and workshop documentation, cassette and video tapes, films, and graphics. Includes papers generated by Knowles as professor (Boston University and North Carolina State University); as member of a number of adult education organizations; as educator (workshops and seminars); and as consultant to various organizations.
Major correspondents and/or individuals with printed/published material in the collection include George F. Aker, Eugene Eli DuBois, Philip H. DuBois, Stanley M. Grabowski, Cyril Orvin Houle, J.R. Kidd, Alan Boyd Knox, Imogene E. Okes, Matilda G. Paisley, King M. Wientge, and Betty H. Wiser.
149396
Biographical History
Malcolm S. Knowles (1913-1997) was an American adult education scholar, consultant, and professor.
Malcolm S. Knowles was born August 24, 1913 in Livingston, Montana. Following his graduation from Palm Beach, Florida High School in 1930, he enrolled in Harvard College where he obtained his A.B. in 1934. He completed his academic studies at the University of Chicago by earning an M.A. in 1949 and a Ph.D. in 1960. He married Hulda Fornell in 1935 by whom he had two children; Eric (1941) and Barbara E. Hartl (1946).
During his early career years, Malcolm S. Knowles held administrative positions with the National Youth Administration of Massachusetts and YMCAs in Boston, Detroit and Chicago. From 1951-1959 he was Executive Director of the Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA/USA). Under his leadership, Knowles helped to establish the Commission of Professors of Adult Education as an affiliated association of the AEA/USA. From 1960-1974 he was a Professor of Education at Boston University. With the start of the fall semester, 1974 he taught as Professor of Adult and Community Education at North Carolina State University in Raleigh until his retirement in 1979.
In addition to his administrative and teaching duties, Malcolm S. Knowles was actively involved as a consultant to numerous corporations, associations and organizations and wrote several books: Informal Adult Education; Teaching Adults in Informal Courses; How to Develop Better Leaders; Introduction to Group Dynamics; Handbook of Adult Education in the U.S.; The Adult Education Movement in the U.S.; Higher Adult Education in the U.S.; The Modern Practice of Adult Education; The Adult Learner: A Neglected Species; Self-Directed Learning: A Guide for Learners and Teachers; and A History of the Adult Education Movement in the U.S. He has authored many other monographs, book chapters and journal articles.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Malcolm S. Knowles Papers contains not only Dr. Knowles' papers, but also papers from various individuals, associations, organizations, and corporations concerned with adult education. Included in the collection are organizational information, biographical data, personal and business correspondence, meetings files, photographs, printed and published material, meetings files, scrapbooks, speeches, workshop files, and audio-visual material (cassette and video tapes, films, and graphics). Pamphlet series items have been added to university's adult education picture and pamphlet files.
The organizations of importance to the collection are:
Adult Education Association of Massachusetts
Adult Education Association of the U.S.A.
Algonquin College of Applied Arts & Technology
American Association of Adult and Continuing Education
American Association for Adult Education
American Library Association
American Society for Training and Development
Boston University
Commission of Professors of Adult Education
Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange
Cooperative Assessment of Experiential Learning
Council for the Advancement of Experiential Learning
General Electric Company
Girl Scouts of the United States of America
International Congress of University Adult Education
International Federation of Training and Development Organizations
Johns Hopkins University
McBer and Company - Institute for Competency Assessment
National Academy for Health Inservice Education
National Center for Education
National Institute for Mental Health
National University Consortium
National University Extension Association
North Carolina State University
Ontario Institute for Studies in Education
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
U.S. Civil Service Commission
U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare
U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare - National Institute of Education
Young Men's Christian Associations
Individuals with significant contributions to the collection are:
George F. Aker
Eugene E. DuBois
Philip H. DuBois
Stanley M. Grabowski
Cyril O. Houle
J.R. Kidd
Alan Boyd Knox
Imogene E. Okes
Matilda G. Paisley
King M. Wientge
Betty H. Wiser
Arrangement of the Collection
Associations includes all information specific to the identity of an organization with which Knowles had some affiliation. The series is arranged alphabetically by name of association. Designated materials are annual reports, informational pamphlets, constitutions, and directories. Biographical series has vitae arranged alphabetically. Correspondence - business comprises letters to and from Knowles, grouped by subject matter (i.e., letters connected with an organization or writing project of Knowles). Arrangement is alphabetical by subject and chronological arrangement rules within a subject. Correspondence - personal contains daily correspondence to and from Knowles. The arrangement is chronological.
Meetings files contains files that Knowles maintained for conferences and other meetings which he attended. The meetings are identified by their sponsors which appear in alphabetical order. Multiple meetings by a single sponsor are further divided by date (earliest to latest) or conference title. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by identifier.
Printed material (substantive works such as organization publications, articles, journals, papers, and grant proposals) is arranged alphabetically by, in most instances, corporate body or title of work for personal authors. Articles by Knowles will not be found under title, however; these appear under the subseries "Articles by Knowles." Knowles' other papers are interfiled by title among all printed material. Published material comprises material that has an identifiable copyright. Arrangement is alphabetical by corporate author or title as is the case for personal authors or works without a stated author.
Knowles' Scrapbooks chronicle his late adolescence and early career years. They are ordered alphabetically by scrapbook name. Workshop files consists of the documentation that Knowles kept for workshops he conducted. The files are arranged alphabetically by workshop sponsor or title if no sponsor is identified. In cases of multiple workshops by a single sponsor an alphabetical and/or chronological order takes over.
Finally, Audio-visual contains graphics, films and tapes (videocassette, audiocassette and reel-to-reel). Material is grouped by type and within type is ordered alphabetically.
Due to the arrangement of material by type, a given individual or organization may appear in several of the series -- for example, Boston University appears in Associations, Printed material, Speeches, and Workshop files. The researcher is advised to review the entire finding aid to ensure no relevant material is overlooked.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A large number of books came with the collection, a complete list of which can be found in Biographical material: List of books in Knowles' library. For the most part, these were duplicates of existing holdings and during Aug 2006 reprocessing they were discarded. A few were sent to Rare Books for cataloging and may be located through, by searching for "Malcolm S. Knowles" as a keyword.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Aker, George F.; DuBois, Eugene Eli, 1937-; DuBois, Philip H. (Philip Hunter), 1903-1998.; Grabowski, Stanley M.; Houle, Cyril O. (Cyril Orvin), 1913-1998.; Kidd, J. R. (James Robbins), 1915-1982.; Knowles, Malcolm S. (Malcolm Shepherd), 1913-1997.; Knox, Alan B. (Alan Boyd), 1931-; Mezirow, Jack, 1923-2014.; Okes, Imogene E.; Paisley, Matilda G.; Wientge, King M.; Wiser, Betty H. (Betty Hutchinson); Adult Education Association.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; American Association for Adult Education.; American Society for Training and Development.; Commission of Professors of Adult Education.; Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange.; Cooperative Assessment of Experiential Learning (U.S.); Council for the Advancement of Experiential Learning (U.S.); International Congress of University Adult Education.; International Federation of Training and Development Organizations.; National University Extension Association.; YMCA of the USA.; YWCA.; Adult education -- Study and teaching.; Adult education -- United States.; Andragogy.; Educators -- United States.; Professional education.; Training manuals.; Annual reports.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Correspondence.; Directories.; Manuals (instructional materials); Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Consultants.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Malcolm Shepherd Knowles
Inventory
- Associations
  - Alcohol and Drug Problems Association of North America, Summer Schools of Alcohol/Drug Studies, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Adult Continuing Education, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education Association of Massachusetts, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA/USA)
    - Annual reports, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
    - Association information, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Commission on Research, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Information and membership cards, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Organization history and information (Box 1)
  - Adult Referral and Information Services in Education, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Adult Student Personnel Association, Inc. (ASPA), 1969 (Box 1)
  - American Association for Adult Education & National Education Association, Joint Committee, 1950 (Box 1)
  - American Educational Research Association (AERA), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - American Society for Training and Development (ASTD), Professional Development Committee, 1976; 1978 (Box 1)
  - Bentley College, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Boston College Evening College, undated (Box 1)
  - Boston University
    - Continuing studies and educational services, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Information pamphlet, 1967 (Box 1)
    - School of Education
      - Department of Administration and Supervision, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Department of Community College and Continuing Education, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - Graduate program in adult education, undated (Box 1)
  - California Western University, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Catholic Diocese of Richmond Ministries Formation Program, undated (Box 1)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
    - Annual reports, 1960; 1961 (Box 1)
    - Brochure draft, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Brochure, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Membership directories, 1960; 1963-1967,; 1969-1971,; 1973,; 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Membership information, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Task Force on Instructional Improvement, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 68)
  - Continuing Education Council, undated (Box 1)
  - Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Data Education Inc., 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Delaware Community College, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Educational Resources Information Center (ERIC)
    - Clearinghouse in Career Education, undated (Box 2)
    - Clearinghouse on Adult Education, undated (Box 2)
  - Federal National Mortgage Association, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Fielding Institute, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Flint (Michigan) Community Schools, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Florida State University, Department of Adult Education, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - George Washington University, Institute for Educational Leadership, undated (Box 2)
  - Illinois State University, Kellogg Project, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Institute for Organizational Behavior and Human Resource Development, undated (Box 2)
  - International Association of Chiefs of Police, Theft Prevention and Property Recovery Program, undated (Box 2)
  - International Federation of Training and Development Organizations, undated (Box 2)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Maryland State Department of Education, Adult Basic Education/Instructional Television Project, 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Board of Higher Education, Advisory Council on Continuing Education, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Massachusetts Department of Mental Health
    - Community Mental Health and Mental Retardation Area Boards, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Continuing Education in Mental Health, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Monash University, undated (Box 3)
  - Murdoch University, Educational Services and Teaching Resources Unit, undated (Box 3)
  - National Academy for Health Inservice Education
    - Board of Directors list and photograph (Box 3)
    - By-laws, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Informational pamphlets, undated (Box 3)
  - National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) Professional Development Committee, undated (Box 3)
  - National Center for Educational Statistics, 1978 (Box 3)
  - National Defense University
    - Curriculum guides, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Report, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - National Training Laboratory Institute for Applied Behavioral Science, Professional Development Learning Communities, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Nebraska Educational Television Council for Higher Education, Inc., undated (Box 3)
  - New York State Education Department, Office of Doctoral Projects, Rating Committee in Higher and Adult Education, 1979 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Adult Education Association, Task Force on Educational Brokering for North Carolina, 1977 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina State University, Department of Adult and Community College Education, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Oakland Community College, Personalized Educational Program, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Ontario Institute for Studies in Education (OISE), undated (Box 4)
  - Overseas Education Fund of the League of Women Voters, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Pittsburgh Public Schools, Task Force on Community Use of Building Facilities, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Project Associates, Inc., 1973 (Box 4)
  - R.A. Dinkel and Associates, Adult Education Promotion Services, undated (Box 4)
  - Rutgers University
    - Department of Extension, circa 1951 (Box 4)
    - University Extension Division, Labor Education Center
      - Annual report, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Proposed program and asking budget, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Society of Professional Adult Educators (SPAE), undated (Box 4)
  - State University of Nebraska, undated (Box 4)
  - Unitarian Universalist Service Committee, undated (Box 4)
  - United States Department of Agriculture Extension Service
    - 4-H youth development enrollment report, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Cooperative Extension Service programs, 1976 (Box 4)
  - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW)
    - Health Services and Mental Health Administration, 1969 (Box 4)
    - National Center for Health Services Research and Development, undated (Box 4)
    - National Institute of Education (NIE)
      - Dissemination and Resources Group, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Informational pamphlet, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Preliminary fiscal year 1978 program plans, 1976 (Box 4)
    - National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)
      - Continuing Education Review Committee, 1969-1972; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Universidad nacional experimental Simon Rodriguez, undated (Box 4)
  - University of Colorado Extension Division, Adult Education Project Region VIII, 1970 (Box 5)
  - University of Southern California School of Public Administration, 1976; 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - William Rainey Harper College, Professional Development Project, Human Resource Development Committee, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), Organization Development Program, 1961-1966 (Box 5)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) of Canada, National Council, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) of the Philippines, Rizal Youth Leadership Training Foundation, 1962 (Box 5)
- Biographical material
  - Biographical summary of Malcolm S. Knowles (Box 5)
  - DuBois, Eugene E., c.v. (Box 5)
  - Evaluations (Box 67)
  - List of books in Knowles' library (Box 5)
    Most of these are available in the library's general collection. Please search by author or title for more information on individual books.
- Correspondence
  - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA/USA), National Association of Professors of Continuing and Adult Education (NAPCAE), American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), Jan 1968-Jul 1982 (Box 5)
  - American Council on Education (ACE), Nov 1965-Feb 1973 (Box 5)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), Dec 1959-Nov 1975; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Fan letters (Box 68)
  - Girl Scouts of the United States of America, Jan 1964-Nov 1972 (Box 5)
  - Letters to and from Knowles about his book, Materials and methods in adult education, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Letters to and from Knowles about his book, Informal education, Jan 1961-Dec 1964 (Box 5)
  - Letters to and from Knowles about his book, Modern practice of adult education, Jun 1968-Jul 1973 (Box 6)
  - National Academy for Health Inservice Education, Jul 1970-Feb 1972 (Box 6)
  - Personal correspondence, 1951-1969; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Personal correspondence, 1970-1972; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Personal correspondence, 1973-1974; 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Personal correspondence, 1975; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Personal correspondence, 1976-Jun 1977; 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Personal correspondence, Jul 1977-Nov 1978; 7 folders (Box 11)
  - Personal correspondence, Dec 1978-Jun 1980; 8 folders (Box 12)
  - Personal correspondence, Jul 1980-Sep 1981; 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Personal correspondence, Oct 1981-Mar 1983; 5 folders (Box 14)
  - Personal correspondence, Apr 1983-Dec 1984; 6 folders (Box 15)
  - Personal correspondence, 1985; 2 folders (Box 16)
- Meetings files
  - Academy for Educational Development, Conference on the significance of the biomedical and the social sciences in understanding the aging process, 1976 (Box 16)
  - Adult Education Association of Massachusetts
    - Program, 1972 (Box 16)
    - Annual conference on learning strategies for adult education, 1971 (Box 16)
  - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA/USA)
    - Ad Hoc Committee of Adult Education Organizations, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Annual, 1967-1968; 1970-1977; 10 folders (Box 16)
    - Annual, 1978-1980; 1982; 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Committee on Professional Standards in Adult Education, 1968 (Box 17)
    - Consultation on classification problems in organizing adult education libraries and clearinghouses, 1966 (Box 17)
    - Council of National Organizations, 1958 (Box 17)
    - Delegate Assembly, 1954-1955; 1957-1958; 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Executive Committee, 1951; 1956,; 1960; 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Publication Committee, 1976-1978 (Box 17)
    - 2nd Executive Committee, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Adult Education Research Conference (AERC), 1970; 1972; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Adventures in learning today's world, 1974 (Box 17)
  - American Alumni Council Fund for Adult Education, Shoreham conference on continuing education for alumni, 1956 (Box 17)
  - American Management Association, Management of human resources through behavioral sciences, 1970 (Box 17)
  - American Medical Writers Association, 40th Annual Conference, 1980 (Box 17)
  - American Psychiatric Association, Committee on Continuing Education, 1974 (Box 17)
  - American Society for Training and Development (ASTD)
    - Professional Development Committee, 1975-1978 (Box 17)
    - 24th National Conference, 1968 (Box 17)
  - Arizona State University
    - Department of Higher and Adult Education - Higher and Adult Education Alumni Board Professional continuing education conference, 1980 (Box 18)
    - Graduate Program in Adult Education & Arizona Adult Education Association (Box 18)
    - Spring conference, 1972 (Box 18)
  - Association of Southern Baptist Colleges and Schools, annual conference, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), Conference of adult education organizations (CAEO), 1965 (Box 18)
  - Association of Volunteer Bureaus, Inc., 25th Anniversary & Annual Conference, 1976 (Box 18)
  - Castleton State College Andragogy conference, 1971 (Box 18)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO) Wingspread Conference, 1976 (Box 18)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
    - Ann Arbor Conference, 1957 (Box 18)
    - Annual conference, 1961; 1964-1972; 10 folders (Box 18)
    - Annual conference, 1974-1976; 1978,; 1982; 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Business, 1964 (Box 19)
    - Continuity Committee, 1961 (Box 19)
    - East Lansing Conference, 1960 (Box 19)
    - Executive Committee, 1965-1966; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Connecticut conference on adult and higher education, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Connecticut Nurses' Association, 1971 (Box 19)
  - Continuing Education Council Accrediting Commission, 1974-1976 (Box 19)
  - Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange, 1st Assembly, 1976 (Box 19)
  - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, Adult Education Conference, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Council of Professional Organizations of the American Society of Allied Health Professions, Invitational conference on continuing education for health professional organizations, 1978 (Box 19)
  - Council on Social Work Education, 18th annual, 1971 (Box 19)
  - Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU), 4th annual, 1982 (Box 19)
  - Episcopal Church, General Convention, 1969 (Box 19)
  - Florida Junior College at Jacksonville, Adult and continuing education in-service training conference, 1970 (Box 20)
  - Florida State Department of Education, 2d annual vocational, technical and adult educators' conference, 1969 (Box 20)
  - Galaxy Conference, 1969 (Box 20)
  - General Board of Lay Activities of the Methodist Church, 1967; consultation on the laity (Box 20)
  - Growth Associates, National conference on self-directed professional development, 1977 (Box 20)
  - Harvard University Graduate School of Education, Closing the gap: higher education and the low income adult, 1974 (Box 20)
  - Human Resources Development, 9th Annual HRD college for trainers, 1982 (Box 20)
  - International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE)
    - Executive Committee, 1964 (Box 20)
    - World (or International) conference, 1965; 1970; 1972; first, second, and third; 3 folders (Box 20)
  - International Federation of Training and Development Organizations
    - 4th Interamerican symposium on training development, 1976 (Box 20)
    - 6th International conference on training and development of human resources, 1977 (Box 20)
    - 11th International training and development world congress, 1982 (Box 20)
  - Johns Hopkins University Evening College Task Force for Community Service and Continuing Education, 1972-1974 (Box 20)